A Finding Aid to the Sharon Frances Patton Research Material Regarding Vincent Smith, 1968-2005, in the Archives of American Art AAA.smitvinc
Archives of American Art
Sharon Frances Patton research material regarding Vincent Smith
1968-2005
AAA.smitvinc
Archives of American Art
0.8 Linear feet
The Sharon Frances Patton research material on the artist Vincent Smith measures 0.8 linear feet and dates from 1968-2005. Materials document Smith’s career as an artist and include many letters as well as autobiographical writings by him. Also featured in this collection are many printed materials relating to his career including magazines, exhibition materials and clippings. This collection also includes three sound cassettes featuring a profile of Smith and his thoughts on music.
Patton, Sharon F.
Arrangement note
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1980-2004 (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1982-1998 (2 folders; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, 1976-circa 1994 (5 folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1968-2005 (0.4 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
Series 5: Sound Recordings, 1986-1989 (3 folders; Box 2)
The collection is arranged as 5 series:
Biographical/Historical note
Sharon Frances Patton (1944- ) is a art historian and museum director in Baltimore, Maryland. Vincent Smith (1929-2003) was a painter from New York City. His work was exhibited extensively and is now part of many distinguished collections.
Patton earned her BA in humanities with an emphasis on Studio Art from Roosevelt University in Chicago. This was followed by an MA from University of Illinois, Champaign-Urbana and a Ph.D. in African Art History at Northwestern University. During and after these degrees she was a professor at various colleges around the country as well as a curator at the Studio Museum in Harlem, the Director of the Center for African American Studies at University of Michigan and the Director of the Allen Memorial Art Museum at Oberlin College. From 2003-2008 she was the Director of the Smithsonian’s National Museum of African Art. Throughout her career she has organized around 20 exhibitions, compiled catalogs (one of which was on Vincent Smith’s “Riding on a Blue Note” exhibit), written articles and essays and given lectures. She has also written two books, Memory and Metaphor: The Art of Romare Bearden and African American Art.
Smith became a full-time artist in 1953 after stints as a hobo, in the army and as a post office worker. Around this time he studied art at the Brooklyn Museum Art School, New York City’s Art Students League and attended the Skowhegan School of Painting and Sculpture in Maine on a scholarship. He also cited other African American artists as valuable resources for the development of his work. Much of his early work focused on the culture of jazz in New York City, but in the mid-1950s, with the start of the Civil Rights Movement, his work took on a more political tone. His first solo show was in 1955 at the Brooklyn Museum Art School Gallery and this was followed by many more solo and group shows throughout his career. His work is now in the collections of many museums as well as President Clinton, who was given one of Smith’s pieces at his first inauguration. In 1980 he received a college degree from Empire State College at the State University of New York, Saratoga.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated by Sharon Frances Patton in 2012.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Scope and Contents note
The Sharon Frances Patton research material on the artist Vincent Smith measures 0.8 linear feet and dates from 1968-2005. The research materials document Smith’s career as an artist and include many letters as well as autobiographical writings by him. Also featured in this collection are many printed materials relating to his career including magazines, exhibition materials and clippings. This collection also includes three sound cassettes featuring a profile of Smith and his thoughts on music.
Smith, Vincent, 1929-; African American artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Sound recordings
- Biographical Material, 1980-2004; Series 1; 3 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Found here are a curriculum vitae, photographs and an obituary of Vincent Smith. The seven photographs feature Smith, his family and his artwork.
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, circa 1980-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Obituary, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1982-1998; Series 2; 2 Folders Box 1
  Correspondence includes letters written by Vincent Smith to Sharon Frances Patton in which he provides thoughts on travel, personal events and the African American experience. Also included here are letters to Patton by others regarding Smith, including attached photocopied newspaper clippings about one of his shows, and Minnie Evans.
  - Letters to Sharon Frances Patton from Vincent Smith, 1982-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters from Others to Sharon Frances Patton, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Writings, 1976-circa 1994; Series 3; 5 Folders Box 1
  Included here are writings by both Sharon Frances Patton and Vincent Smith. From Smith are two artist statements, a description of study regarding the "Methodology and Philosophy of African American Artists/Dialogues with Contemporary Artists", some of his autobiographical notes and some notes on art. From Patton are some of her notes on Smith, possibly from an interview.
  - Artist Statements, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Description of Study, circa 1990s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Vincent Smith’s Autobiographical Notes, 1978-1982 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sharon Frances Patton’s Notes on Vincent Smith, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Vincent Smith’s Notes on Art, circa 1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Printed Material, 1968-2005; Series 4; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Printed Material contains various publications including several issues of the National Murals Network International Newsletter and Community Murals magazine. Also included are press releases and exhibition publications regarding Vincent Smith’s exhibitions from 1986-2005 as well as magazine and newspaper clippings featuring Smith from 1968-1994. There are a few miscellaneous printed materials including a series of notecards featuring reproductions of Smith’s paintings, information about another artists’ show and a book jacket.
  - National Murals Network International Newsletter, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Community Murals Magazine, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Community Murals Magazine, 1984-1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Magazines, Journals and Anthologies, circa 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Press Releases, 1981-circa 1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Magazine and Newspaper Clippings, 1968-1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Publications, 1969-1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Exhibition Publications, 1980-1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Exhibition Publications, 1990-2005 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Materials, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Sound Recordings, 1986-1989; Series 5; 3 Folders Box 2
  Found here are three sound cassettes. One features a profile of Vincent Smith by David Driskell and Peter Mark from his radio show, "Vincent Smith Dialogues" on WBAI-FM radio and the others are entitled "Vincent D. Smith’s Tapes on Music".
  - Profile of Vincent D. Smith, 1988; Includes one sound cassette. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Vincent Smith’s Tapes on Music, 1989; Includes two sound cassettes. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Artists Featured on "Vincent Smith Dialogues", 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)